RG 142, General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut
Connecticut State Library
General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut records
1896-2012
Connecticut State Library
General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut
34.50 cubic feet
The Connecticut State Federation of Women's Clubs was founded on April 20, 1897 in Bridgeport, Connecticut. The purpose of the federation was to bring women's clubs from around the state into greater communication with one another to increase their members' participation in social, intellectual, and civic activities. From its beginnings, the federation demonstrated a wide breadth of interests, including home economics, literacy, environmental conservation, and the rights and well-being of women and children. In 1984, in order to more accurately reflect its connection to its worldwide parent organization, the federation changed its name to the General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut. The records consist of minutes, correspondence, press books, scrapbooks, programs, directories, sound recordings, videos, and removable media.
RG142
Multiple
Historical Note
In March 1889, Sorosis, a women's club in New York City, founded by journalist Jane Cunningham Croly, held a national convention of women's clubs to celebrate its twenty-first anniversary. During the convention, the delegates voted to form a General Federation of Women's Clubs. Among the attendees was the Kozy Klub of Bridgeport. The following April, Sorosis sponsored another meeting of clubs interested in joining the new federation. Delegates from three Connecticut clubs were among those representing sixty-three women's clubs: the Waterbury Woman's Club, the Willimantic Woman's Club, and the Saturday Club of New London.1 A constitution for the federation was adopted on April 24, 1890, in which the federation's stated mission was to "…bring into communication with each other the various women's clubs throughout the world, in order that they may compare methods of work and become mutually helpful."2
From its beginnings, the General Federation of Women's Clubs displayed a wide range of interests. At its biennial convention in 1896 in Louisville, Kentucky, reports were heard from departments and committees on Literature, Education, Home, Philanthropy, Social Economics, Finance, and Sociology. Papers presented at the convention ranged in subject matter from "Household Economics and the Chemistry of Body-Building" to "Women in Trades and Professions."3
The Connecticut State Federation of Women's Clubs was organized on April 20, 1897 through the initiative of the English Literary Club of Bridgeport and the efforts of Mariana Slade Hopson, the State Chairman of Correspondence for the General Federation. One of the oldest and most distinguished associations in the state, the Bridgeport club organized a meeting with other Connecticut clubs. Representatives of forty-seven organizations, numbering around one hundred delegates, met in the parlors of the South Church of Bridgeport. After registering the member clubs and drafting a constitution, the delegates elected its first officers. Mrs. T.K. Noble4 of Norwalk served as the state federation's first president from 1897-1900.5
The Connecticut federation's objective was to "…bring the women's clubs of the state into communication for intellectual culture, mutual help and social union, and to extend their influence in such matters as may properly come before them for improvement in homes and communities."6 Like its national counterpart, the Connecticut federation demonstrated a breadth of interests and community involvement. The first Official Directory of the state federation, published in 1900, lists several standing committees, including Civics and Village Improvement, Industrial Conditions, and Education, including Travelling Libraries, and Art Interchange. Among the standing committees in 1900 was also one for the Investigation of Connecticut Guardianship Law. The women of the Connecticut federation were particularly interested in the aspects of the law that governed parental rights over minor children. The state federation's Committee on Equal Parental Rights reported extensively to a meeting of its Board of Directors on December 27, 1900, persuading the Board to hire a lawyer to draft a bill to be placed before the Connecticut General Assembly on equal parental guardianship.7
Child welfare and the rights of women continued to be important concerns of the Connecticut federation. In a 1906 presentation to the federation's council about "Vital Questions before the Biennial Convention," club member Mary Williams Phipps addressed the problem of child labor, saying that "It is being urged that the government appoint a child labor bureau…"8 On a national level, General Federation member and Hull House founder Jane Addams simultaneously advocated for the creation of child labor laws. At the same meeting where Mrs. Phipps gave her presentation, Mrs. Frank C. Porter of New Haven read a paper titled, "What Can We Do for Our Factory Girls." In November 1907, the efforts of the state federation to help female factory workers culminated in the appointment of the first female factory inspector in the state.9
The Connecticut federation has also evinced a strong interest in environmental conservation. In 1901, the federation formed a Forestry Committee which, in 1906, supported "Forestry Reservation Bills" for the purpose of planting trees "in waste places free of charge."10 Under the administrations of four different statewide presidents, the federation raised funds to purchase fifty acres of land in Barkhamsted that were donated to the State of Connecticut in 1938, as an addition to the People's Forest. Known as "Constitution Grove", the land was donated as a tribute to Connecticut as the Constitution State. In 1965, in concert with the Sears Roebuck Foundation, the Connecticut Federation of Women's Clubs established the Greenwoods Nature & Conservation Camp for Girls. Three years later, the federation's Conservation Department worked with the Connecticut Girl Scout Council to present a "Cadette Conservation Day," intended to help the state's Girl Scouts become aware of the importance of environmental conservation.
The organizational structure of the Connecticut federation has evolved and solidified, over time. Standing committees that were founded at the start of the organization were renamed as "departments" in 1923, and the federation was incorporated under Connecticut law in 1926. Within a few years of its founding, the federation renamed its board of directors as an executive board, and, in 1928, formed an executive committee to handle any emergency business between meetings. In addition, the federation created, at its inception, a council comprised of the presidents of the federation's individual clubs, whose purpose was to "consider and promote such measures as shall be for the interests of the Federation."11 The communication gap left by the dissolution of this council in 1974 was filled partially by the publication, beginning in that year, of the federation's first statewide guidebook for individual club leaders, Pointers for Participation. The federation's official policy of cooperating on two-year State Projects, instituted in 1972, has also helped the organization maintain its cohesiveness and purpose. In 1984, in order to more accurately reflect its connection to the worldwide General Federation, Connecticut's organization changed its official name to the General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut, Inc.
Other forces, however, have sometimes undermined the unity of the statewide organization. In the 1970's, growing tensions between the Connecticut federation's older members and its Juniors and Juniorettes (composed, respectively, of women 40 years of age, and under, and of girls between the ages of 11 and 18) led to a meeting in April of 1979, mediated by Mrs. J. Frank Bryant, the First Vice President of the national General Federation. This and other attempts at reconciliation were unsuccessful, and all of the Junior and Juniorette Clubs left the Connecticut federation during 1979. Their departure constituted a significant loss in membership for the organization: in May of 1979, total statewide membership had been 12,708, but in May of 1980, the total statewide membership was down to 8,942.12
Despite losing over a quarter of its members, the federation continued its involvement in a wide variety of activities. In keeping with the federation's early interest in women's and children's well-being, the organization during the 1980's raised funds for and awareness of battered women and sexually abused children. In May of 1986, at the end of a two-year statewide project, the federation donated $7,000 to Paul & Lisa, Inc., a non-profit organization for the prevention and rehabilitation of sexually abused children. From 1988 through 1990, the federation supported the work of the Fidelco Guide Dog Foundation, the only guide dog school in New England. During the following decade, the federation focused its efforts on supporting literacy, Alzheimer's research, and Alpha Home, a shelter for women recovering from addiction and substance abuse.
Along with its support of already established programs, the federation has also responded to events and crises, as they have occurred. In 2001, following the terrorist attacks on the United States, the federation worked with Discovery Toys to donate hundreds of copies of a book called The Next Place to schools, libraries, and to families of the victims. The Next Place uses comforting language to describe "the next place" after death. In 2011, in response to the growing problem of cyberbullying, the federation adopted an anti-cyberbullying resolution at its state convention and urged Governor Malloy to support new anti-cyberbullying legislation in the Connecticut General Assembly. The federation states on its website today that "Our goal is to be of service to others, improve our social, cultural and physical environment and promote appreciation of the arts. We strive to become responsible leaders in our communities." These comprehensive goals have not deviated far from the federation's stated purpose in 1897.
Endnotes
1 Patricia Andrews, A Century of Women in Volunteer Community Service: The History of the General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut, Inc., 1897-1997, vii, series 4, box 2, folder 12, General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut Records, RG 142, Connecticut State Library.
2 Jennie Cunningham Croly, The History of the Woman's Club Movement in America (New York: Henry G. Allen & Co., 1898), 98.
3 Ibid., 172-173.
4 Records often list married members only by their husbands' first names.
5 Andrews, iii.
6 Mariana Slade Hopson, "Article II, Constitution", series 1, box 1, volume "Minutes of Board, Council and State: April 20, 1897-Nov. 9, 1900", p. 15, General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut Records, RG 142, Connecticut State Library.
7 Mary Louise Barroll, "Minutes of the 22nd Meeting of the Board of Directors, Connecticut State Federation of Women's Clubs", series 1, box 1, volume "Minutes of Executive Board Meetings Nov. 7, 1900 - May 23, 1914", pp. 4-5, General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut Records, RG 142, Connecticut State Library.
8 Mary Williams Phipps, "Vital Questions before the Biennial Convention," series 1, box 1, volume "Minutes of Annual and Council Meetings, May 10, 1901 - June 9, 1916", p. 77, General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut Records, RG 142, Connecticut State Library. Mary William Phipps served as the president of the Connecticut State Federation of Women's Clubs from 1908-1912.
9
(Hartford, Conn.: Office of the Secretary of State, 1842-1929), 850.
10 Eva Child Mason, "Minutes of the 53rd Meeting of the Executive Board of the Connecticut State Federation of Women's Clubs," series 1, box 1, volume "Minutes of Executive Board Meetings, Nov. 7, 1900 - May 23, 1914", pp 77-78, General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut Records, RG 142, Connecticut State Library.
11 Mariana Slade Hopson, "Article III, Section IV, Constitution," series 1, box 1, volume "Minutes of Board, Council and State: April 20, 1897-Nov. 9, 1900", p. 17, General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut Records, RG 142, Connecticut State Library.
12 Shirley G. Meo, "Membership Report, CSFWC State Convention, May 6, 1980," series 1, box 28, folder 2 of 2 "Conventions and Conferences, 1978-1980", General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut Records, RG 142, Connecticut State Library.
Scope and Content
The records are arranged into nine series which document the organization and activities of the General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut. The series include: Administrative Files, Publications, Press Books and Scrapbooks, Centennial, Photographs, Artifacts, Sound Recordings, Videos, and Removable Media.
Series 1. Administrative Files, 1896-2012, include minutes, reports, correspondence, calls to meetings, programs, directories, bylaws, official ballots, and newspaper clippings.
Series 2. Publications, 1898-1972, consist of histories, newsletters, directories, and club year books.
Series 3. Press Books and Scrapbooks, 1897-1957, consist primarily of scrapbooks of newspaper clippings and other published accounts of the activities of the General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut. The series also includes records of press book contests held by the federation.
Series 4. Centennial, 1995-1998, includes correspondence, reports, minutes, calls to meetings, programs, and directories of the federation's centennial administration. The series also contains records of the federation's centennial celebration, held in May 1997.
Series 5. Photographs, 1976, consist of one box of photographic slides from a home energy check slide show.
Series 6. Artifacts, 1897-2011, include a delegate's badge, a medal, a guestbook, and a stamp of a woman's likeness, most likely of statewide president, Florence Sutton.
Series 7. Sound Recordings, 1953-1963, consists of sound recordings, on vinyl records, of speakers at the Eastern Region General Federation of Women's Clubs Convention in 1953, and at the Annual Conventions in 1953, 1954, and 1963. Also includes a recording, on vinyl records, of a federation song, "Strengthen the Arm of Liberty."
Series 8. Videos, circa 2009-2010, consists of 2 duplicate digital video discs on the Veterans OASIS project and 1 digital video disc on the American Mural Project.
Series 9. Removable Media, 2008-2010, consists of 37 Microsoft Word documents including executive committee and board minutes; convention planning minutes; convention bullet points; orientation minutes; and an index of meeting dates.
Arrangement
Series 1. Administrative Files, 1896-2012
Series 2. Publications, 1898-1972
Series 3. Press Books and Scrapbooks, 1897-1957
Series 4. Centennial, 1995-1998
Series 5. Photographs, 1976
Series 6. Artifacts, 1897-2011
Series 7. Sound Recordings, 1953-1963
Series 8. Videos, circa 2009-2010
Series 9. Removable Media, 2008-2010
Related Material
website.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut State Federation of Women's Clubs; General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut
Subjects:
General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut -- Records and correspondence; Women -- Societies and clubs; Women -- Connecticut -- Societies and clubs
Document Types:
Brochures; Clippings; Correspondence; Financial Records; Histories; Legal Documents; Minutes; Photographs; Programs (documents); Publications; Reports; Scrapbooks; Yearbooks; DVDs; Compact discs
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The following accessions were donated by the General Federation of Women's Clubs of Connecticut to the Connecticut State Library:
Accession 1986-034 was donated on October 28, 1986.
Accession 1987-029 was donated on May 15, 1987.
Accession 1992-089 was donated on June 25, 1992.
Accession 1996-018 was donated on January 31, 1996.
Accession 2001-028 was donated on July 29, 1996.
Accession 2002-022 was donated on July 16, 2001.
Accession 2002-085 was donated on December 10, 2001.
Accession 2003-018 was donated on September 19, 2002.
Accession 2005-007 was donated on November 10, 2004.
Accession 2009-008 was donated on September 4, 2008.
Accession 2013-024 was donated on January 10, 2013.
Accession T001324 was combined into T001355 in April 2013.
Accession 2016-009 was donated on November 13, 2015.
Container List
- Series 1. Administrative Files, 1896-2012
  - T001355
    - Minutes of board, council and state, 1896 November 16-1900 November 9; 1 volume (Box 1)
      The starting date on the spine of the volume is recorded incorrectly as 1897.
    - Minutes of executive board meetings, 1900 November 7-1914 May 21; 1 volume (Box 1)
    - Minutes of annual and council meetings, 1901 May 10-1916 June 9; 1 volume (Box 1)
    - Minutes of executive board meetings, 1914 September 10-1928 September 22; 1 volume (Box 1)
    - Registrations at annual meetings of the state federation of women's clubs, 1914-1918; 1 volume (Box 1)
    - Minutes of state meetings, 1916 October 25-1928 May 17; 1 volume (Box 2)
      Pages of volume are interleaved with clippings, programs, and official ballots.
    - Minutes of executive board, committee and state meetings of the Connecticut State Federation of Women's Clubs, Inc., 1934 June 11-1938 May 4; 1 volume (Box 3)
    - Minutes of state meetings executive board committee, 1938 June 21-1941 April 4; 1 volume (Box 3)
    - Minutes of executive board meetings, 1941 May 9-1943 May 6; 1 volume (Box 3)
    - Minutes of the recording secretary, (Mrs. Clifford A. Teeple) Mary M. Teeple, 1943 May 6-1945 May 23; 1 volume (Box 3)
    - Minutes of the recording secretary (Mrs. Elwood E. Folsom, Jr.) Muriel K. Folsom, 1945 June 14-1947 May 15; 1 volume (Box 4)
    - Minutes of the recording secretary (Mrs. John W.) Bessie B. Potter, 1947 June 17-1951 May 19; 1 volume (Box 4)
    - Minutes of recording secretary, Mrs. Paul V. Plummer, 1951 May 3-1953 June 10; 1 volume (Box 5)
    - Records of the administration of Mrs. Douglas A. Johnston, state president, 1951 September 11-1953 May 29; 1 binder (Box 5)
      Includes her letters to the presidents, reports of board meetings, and annual reports. Also includes history of 1951-1953 by Mrs. Ellis F. Clark, historian.
    - Minutes as recorded by Mary F. Browne and copied in this book by (Mrs. Paul V.) Louisa H. Plummer, 1953 May 6-1955 May 3; 1 volume (Box 6)
    - Minutes, treasurer's reports, legislation, 1962 May 3-1964 April 25; 1 binder (Box 6)
    - Guide, programs, reports, yearbook, 1962-1964; 1 binder (Box 6)
    - Minutes, reports, and correspondence, 1980 May 8-1983 April 21; 1 volume (Box 7)
    - Documents, 1897-1906; 8 folders (Box 8)
      Folders are arranged by years. Documents include correspondence and reports related to the founding of the Connecticut State Federation of Women's Clubs, committee reports, programs, speeches, correspondence, and calls to conventions.
    - Documents, 1906-1908; 1 folder (Box 9)
      Includes correspondence, reports, minutes, programs, calls to meetings, newspaper clippings, resolutions, amendments to bylaws, and yearbook.
    - Federated clubs and the factory inspector, 1907 May 30-1907 November 6 (Box 9)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1906-1907 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1903-1909 November 10 (Box 9)
      Includes reports, correspondence, newspaper clippings, and programs.
    - Mrs. W.H. Phipps, president, 1908 November 5-1912 May 18 (Box 9)
    - Mrs. James R. Bolton, president, 1912 October 30-1916 June 9 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence from general federation, 1914 March 5-1916 February 19 (Box 10)
    - Documents, 1912 April 25-1935 June 24; 1 folder (Box 10)
      Includes correspondence, reports, programs, calls to meetings, greetings from state and national federations of women's clubs, historical notes, and Mrs. Bolton's correspondence, while historian.
    - Mrs. E.H. Smiley, president, 1916 March-1918 January 17 (Box 10)
    - Mrs. J.R. Mason, Mrs. H.B. Brainard, presidents, 1918 March 15-1923 March 19 (Box 11)
    - Mrs. George H. Stoughton, president, 1922-1926 May 19; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Emily Louise Plumley, president, 1926 May 24-1930 April 28; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Documents, 1915 November 17-1926 September 30; 1 folder (Box 11)
      Includes correspondence, minutes, including minutes for incorporation, programs, reports, sheet music, calls to meetings, bylaws, and lists of officers.
    - Ye Historie of the English Literary Club, 1879 October-1929 October; 1 booklet (Box 12)
    - Binder cover, 1928 October 28-1934 May 17; photocopy (Box 12)
    - Documents, 1924 September-1934 May 17; 3 envelopes (Box 12)
      Includes calls to meetings, correspondence, minutes, newspaper clippings, official ballots, and reports.
    - Mrs. Robert F. Gadd, president, 1930 October 29-1934 May 17; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Miss Florence L. Sutton, president, 1934 October 25-1938 May 4 (Box 13)
    - Miss Laura Hale Gorton, president, 1938 May 20-1945 March (Box 14)
    - Mrs. Eric V. Johnson, president, 1941 May 7-1943 May 6 (Box 14)
    - Mrs. Robert T. Baldwin, president, 1942 December 29-1945 May 23 (Box 14)
    - Mrs. Elliott I. Petersen, president, 1945 June 27-1947 May 13 (Box 14)
    - Mrs. Elliott I. Petersen, president, 1945 May 6-1947 May 15 (Box 15)
    - Mrs. C. Whitfield Gowrie, president, 1945 April-1949 May 19; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Reports, 1947-1949 April 9 (Box 15)
    - Mrs. Douglas A. Johnston, president, 1951 September 11-1953 May 6 (Box 16)
    - Mrs. Clifford A. Teeple, president, 1951 July 16-1955 May 5 (Box 16)
    - List of clubs and dates organized and federated, 1897-1955; 1 envelope; Includes two histories of the Connecticut federation, 1953-1955 and 1954-1955. (Box 16)
    - Mrs. John Arthur Bjerkoe, president, 1955 May 5-1957 May 9; 1 binder (Box 16)
    - Documents, 1958 May 6-1962 June; Includes a program, certificates of appreciation, and a list of officers and delegates. (Box 17)
    - History, 1957-1958; 1 envelope (Box 17)
    - Minutes, 1957 May 9-1962 May 3; 1 binder (Box 17)
    - Arts and crafts department, 1965 February 4-1966 May 19 (Box 18)
    - Congressional medal of honor project, 1965 October 6-1966 May 11 (Box 18)
    - Conservation department, 1965 May 5-1966 August 1 (Box 18)
    - Conventions, 1964-1966 May 7 (Box 18)
    - County meetings and reports, 1964 October 6-1966 April 26 (Box 18)
    - Book-author lunch, 1965 February 10-1966 February 10 (Box 18)
    - Diamond jubilee, 1965 May 21-1966 January 13 (Box 18)
    - Education department, 1965 April 1-1966 March 20 (Box 18)
    - Executive board, 1964 June 18-1966 March 24 (Box 18)
    - Executive committee, 1964 May 7-1966 May 3 (Box 18)
    - Extension report, 1965 April 1-1966 May 3 (Box 18)
    - Fall conferences, 1964 November 4-1965 October 4 (Box 18)
    - Financial reports, 1963 April 1-1966 April 4 (Box 19)
    - President's memo, 1964 July 28-1966 April 29 (Box 19)
    - Industry tour, 1964 July 28-1966 April 19 (Box 19)
    - International relations department, 1964 August 5-1966 May 5 (Box 19)
    - Choclate [chocolate] candy sale project, 1964 November 30-1964 December 28 (Box 19)
    - Home life department, 1964 November 10-1966 May 4 (Box 19)
    - Junior clubs, 1964 June 27-1966 May 16 (Box 19)
    - New England conference, 1964 March 6-1966 January 2 (Box 19)
    - Public relations, 1964 October 7-1965 April 15 (Box 19)
    - Service bureau, 1966 January 27-1966 April 13 (Box 19)
    - President's council, 1964 June 23-1966 April 4 (Box 19)
    - Public affairs department, 1964 September-1966 March 31 (Box 19)